Microservice Architecture

Context

You are developing a server-side enterprise application. It must support a variety of different clients including desktop browsers, mobile browsers, and native mobile applications. The application might also expose an API for 3rd parties to consume. It might also integrate with other applications via either web services or a message broker. The application handles requests (HTTP requests and messages) by executing business logic; accessing a database; exchanging messages with other systems; and returning an HTML/JSON/XML response. There are logical components corresponding to different functional areas of the application.

Solution

Define an architecture that structures the application as a set of loosely coupled, collaborating services. This approach corresponds to the Y-axis of the The Scale Cube. Each service is:

Highly maintainable and testable - enables rapid and frequent development and deployment

Loosely coupled with other services - enables a team to work independently the majority of time on their service(s) without being impacted by changes to other services and without affecting other services

Independently deployable - enables a team to deploy their service without having to coordinate with other teams

Capable of being developed by a small team - essential for high productivity by avoiding the high communication head of large teams

Services communicate using either synchronous protocols such as HTTP/REST or asynchronous protocols such as AMQP. Services can be developed and deployed independently of one another. Each service has its own database in order to be decoupled from other services. Data consistency between services is maintained using the The saga pattern

To learn more about the nature of a service, please read this article What is a (micro)service?.

Formation Julia du LAL

Titre : Atelier Julien (http://calcul.math.cnrs.fr/spip.php?article259)

Date : 16-17 juin 2015

Lieu : LAL, Orsay

Organisateur : Loic Gouarin

Formateur : David P. Sanders

Participants : TLC

Le langage est encore trop jeune pour être utilisé en “production” :

la syntaxe est encore changeante (type int64 déprécié pour Int64…) ;

certaines constructions crashent (push!(x, x)) ;

il n'y a pour le moment pas de composants logiciel pour la biologie.

Les syntaxes pour paralléliser le code sont “sexy”, mais le formateur ne les utilisant pas, elles ne sont pas présentées. Historiquement, Julia aurait démarré comme une solution alternative à la parallélisation sous MatLab, car celle-ci était impossible à implémenter proprement.

MatLab est beaucoup cité lors des pauses, car les participants cherchent des alternatives qui ne nécessitent pas de payer une licence. Mais, visiblement, personne ne connait Octave ; ils n'ont pas dû beaucoup chercher…

Concernant la formation proprement dite, elle est entièrement basée sur des notebooks iPython qui contiennent les explications et les exercices. Ceux-ci sont disponibles ici : https://github.com/dpsanders/hands_on_julia. Le logiciel Jupyter (anciennement iPython) est utilisé pour travailler sur les notebooks. C'est la bonne surprise de la formation. En effet, plus de 40 langages sont maintenant utilisables !

Parmi les autres outils évoqués, on peut mentionner SageMathCloud qui est “SageMath, IPython, LaTeX, and terminals in your browser”. C'est une interface web fort sympathique pour travailler de manière collaborative sur un grand nombre de types de fichier, dont les notebooks de Jupyter. À essayer !

Working with SSL certificates, priate keys and CSRs

OpenSSL is a versatile command line tool that can be used for a large variety of tasks related to Public Key Infrastructure (PKI) and HTTPS (HTTP over TLS). This cheat sheet style guide provides a quick reference to OpenSSL commands that are useful in common, everyday scenarios. This includes OpenSSL examples of generating private keys, certificate signing requests, and certificate format conversion. It does not cover all of the uses of OpenSSL.

About Certificate Signing Requests (CSRs)

If you would like to obtain an SSL certificate from a certificate authority (CA), you must generate a certificate signing request (CSR). A CSR consists mainly of the public key of a key pair, and some additional information. Both of these components are inserted into the certificate when it is signed.

Whenever you generate a CSR, you will be prompted to provide information regarding the certificate. This information is known as a Distinguised Name (DN). An important field in the DN is the Common Name (CN), which should be the exact Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) of the host that you intend to use the certificate with. It is also possible to skip the interactive prompts when creating a CSR by passing the information via command line or from a file.

The other items in a DN provide additional information about your business or organization. If you are purchasing an SSL certificate from a certificate authority, it is often required that these additional fields, such as “Organization”, accurately reflect your organization's details.

Here is an example of what the CSR information prompt will look like:

---
Country Name (2 letter code) [AU]:US
State or Province Name (full name) [Some-State]:New York
Locality Name (eg, city) []:Brooklyn
Organization Name (eg, company) [Internet Widgits Pty Ltd]:Example Brooklyn Company
Organizational Unit Name (eg, section) []:Technology Division
Common Name (e.g. server FQDN or YOUR name) []:examplebrooklyn.com
Email Address []:

Generating a csr without a private key

Use this method if you want to use HTTPS (HTTP over TLS) to secure your Apache HTTP or Nginx web server, and you want to use a Certificate Authority (CA) to issue the SSL certificate. The CSR that is generated can be sent to a CA to request the issuance of a CA-signed SSL certificate. If your CA supports SHA-2, add the -sha256 option to sign the CSR with SHA-2.

This command creates a 2048-bit private key (domain.key) and a CSR (domain.csr) from scratch:

openssl req \
       -newkey rsa:2048 -nodes -keyout domain.key \
       -out domain.csr

Answer the CSR information prompt to complete the process.

The -newkey rsa:2048 option specifies that the key should be 2048-bit, generated using the RSA algorithm. The -nodes option specifies that the private key should not be encrypted with a pass phrase. The -new option, which is not included here but implied, indicates that a CSR is being generated.

Generating a csr with a private key

This command creates a new CSR (domain.csr) based on an existing private key (domain.key):

openssl req \
       -key domain.key \
       -new -out domain.csr

Answer the CSR information prompt to complete the process.

The -key option specifies an existing private key (domain.key) that will be used to generate a new CSR. The -new option indicates that a CSR is being generated.

Generate a CSR from an Existing Certificate and Private Key

Use this method if you want to renew an existing certificate but you or your CA do not have the original CSR for some reason. It basically saves you the trouble of re-entering the CSR information, as it extracts that information from the existing certificate.

This command creates a new CSR (domain.csr) based on an existing certificate (domain.crt) and private key (domain.key):

openssl x509 \
       -in domain.crt \
       -signkey domain.key \
       -x509toreq -out domain.csr

The -x509toreq option specifies that you are using an X509 certificate to make a CSR.

Generating SSL Certificates (self - signed)

Use this method if you want to use HTTPS (HTTP over TLS) to secure your Apache HTTP or Nginx web server, and you do not require that your certificate is signed by a CA.

This command creates a 2048-bit private key (domain.key) and a self-signed certificate (domain.crt) from scratch:

openssl req \
       -newkey rsa:2048 -nodes -keyout domain.key \
       -x509 -days 365 -out domain.crt

Answer the CSR information prompt to complete the process.

The -x509 option tells req to create a self-signed cerificate. The -days 365 option specifies that the certificate will be valid for 365 days. A temporary CSR is generated to gather information to associate with the certificate.

Generate a Self-Signed Certificate from an Existing Private Key

Use this method if you already have a private key that you would like to generate a self-signed certificate with it.

This command creates a self-signed certificate (domain.crt) from an existing private key (domain.key):

openssl req \
       -key domain.key \
       -new \
       -x509 -days 365 -out domain.crt

Generate a Self-Signed Certificate from an Existing Private Key and CSR

Use this method if you already have a private key and CSR, and you want to generate a self-signed certificate with them.

This command creates a self-signed certificate (domain.crt) from an existing private key (domain.key) and (domain.csr):

openssl x509 \
       -signkey domain.key \
       -in domain.csr \
       -req -days 365 -out domain.crt

The -days 365 option specifies that the certificate will be valid for 365 days.

View Certificate, keys, csrs

Certificate and CSR files are encoded in PEM format, which is not readily human-readable.

This section covers OpenSSL commands that will output the actual entries of PEM-encoded files.

View CSR Entries

This command allows you to view and verify the contents of a CSR (domain.csr) in plain text:

openssl req -text -noout -verify -in domain.csr

View Certificate Entries

This command allows you to view the contents of a certificate(domain.crt) in plain text:

openssl x509 -text -noout -in domain.crt

Verify a Certificate was signed by a CA

Use this command to verify that a certificate (domain.crt) was signed by a specific CA certificate (ca.crt):

Openssl verify -verboose -CAFile ca.crt domain.crt

Private Keys

This section covers OpenSSL commands that are specific to creating and verifying private keys.

Create a Private Key

Use this command to create a password-protected, 2048-bit private key (domain.key):

openssl genrsa -des3 -out domain.key 2048

Enter a password when prompted to complete the process.

Verify a Private Key

Use this command to check that a private key (domain.key) is a valid key:

openssl rsa -check -in domain.key

If your private key is encrypted, you will be prompted for its pass phrase. Upon success, the unencrypted key will be output on the terminal.

Verify a Private Key Matches a Certificate and CSR

Use these commands to verify if a private key (domain.key) matches a certificate (domain.crt) and CSR (domain.csr):

openssl rsa -noout -modulus -in domain.key | openssl md5
# don't know what to do with this
openssl x509 -noout -modulus -in domain.crt | openssl md5
# output certificat with text format
openssl x509 -noout -in ldap.crt -text
#
openssl req -noout -modulus -in domain.csr | openssl md5

If the output of each command is identical there is an extremely high probability that the private key, certificate, and CSR are related.

Encrypt a Private Key

This takes an unencrypted private key (unencrypted.key) and outputs an encrypted version of it (encrypted.key):

openssl rsa -des3 \
       -in unencrypted.key \
       -out encrypted.key

Enter your desired pass phrase, to encrypt the private key with.

Decrypt a Private Key

This takes an encrypted private key (encrypted.key) and outputs a decrypted version of it (decrypted.key):

openssl rsa \
       -in encrypted.key \
       -out decrypted.key

Convert certificate Formats

All of the certificates that we have been working with have been X.509 certificates that are ASCII PEM encoded. There are a variety of other certificate encoding and container types; some applications prefer certain formats over others. Also, many of these formats can contain multiple items, such as a private key, certificate, and CA certificate, in a single file.

OpenSSL can be used to convert certificates to and from a large variety of these formats. This section will cover a some of the possible conversions.

Convert PEM to DER

Use this command if you want to convert a PEM-encoded certificate (domain.crt) to a DER-encoded certificate (domain.der), a binary format:

openssl x509 \
       -in domain.crt \
       -outform der -out domain.der

The DER format is typically used with Java.

Convert DER to PEM

Use this command if you want to convert a DER-encoded certificate (domain.der) to a PEM-encoded certificate (domain.crt):

openssl x509 \
       -inform der -in domain.der \
       -out domain.crt

Convert PEM to PKCS7

Use this command if you want to add PEM certificates (domain.crt and ca-chain.crt) to a PKCS7 file (domain.p7b):

openssl crl2pkcs7 -nocrl \
       -certfile domain.crt \
       -certfile ca-chain.crt \
       -out domain.p7b

Note that you can use one or more -certfile options to specify which certificates to add to the PKCS7 file.

PKCS7 files, also known as P7B, are typically used in Java Keystores and Microsoft IIS (Windows). They are ASCII files which can contain certificates and CA certificates.

Convert PKCS7 to PEM

Use this command if you want to convert a PKCS7 file (domain.p7b) to a PEM file:

openssl pkcs7 \
       -in domain.p7b \
       -print_certs -out domain.crt

Note that if your PKCS7 file has multiple items in it (e.g. a certificate and a CA intermediate certificate), the PEM file that is created will contain all of the items in it.

Convert PEM to PKCS12

Use this command if you want to take a private key (domain.key) and a certificate (domain.crt), and combine them into a PKCS12 file (domain.pfx):

openssl pkcs12 \
       -inkey domain.key \
       -in domain.crt \
       -export -out domain.pfx

You will be prompted for export passwords, which you may leave blank. Note that you may add a chain of certificates to the PKCS12 file by concatenating the certificates together in a single PEM file (domain.crt) in this case.

PKCS12 files, also known as PFX files, are typically used for importing and exporting certificate chains in Micrsoft IIS (Windows).

Convert PKCS12 to PEM

Use this command if you want to convert a PKCS12 file (domain.pfx) and convert it to PEM format (domain.combined.crt):

openssl pkcs12 \
       -in domain.pfx \
       -nodes -out domain.combined.crt

Note that if your PKCS12 file has multiple items in it (e.g. a certificate and private key), the PEM file that is created will contain all of the items in it.

OpenSSL Version

The openssl version command can be used to check which version you are running. The version of OpenSSL that you are running, and the options it was compiled with affect the capabilities (and sometimes the command line options) that are available to you.

The following command displays the OpenSSL version that you are running, and all of the options that it was compiled with:

openssl version -a

First normal form

First normal form (1NF) is a property of a relation in a relational database. A relation is in first normal form if and only if the table have the following qualities:

The table is two-dimensional with rows and columns.

Each row contains data that pertains to some thing or portion of a thing.

Each column contains data for a single attribute of the thing it’s describing.

Each cell (intersection of a row and a column) of the table must have only a single value.

Entries in any column must all be of the same kind. If, for example, the entry in one row of a column contains an employee name, all the other rows must contain employee names in that column, too.

Each column must have a unique name.

No two rows may be identical (that is, each row must be unique).

The order of the columns and the order of the rows are not significant.

First normal form is an essential property of a relation in a relational database. Database normalization is the process of representing a database in terms of relations in standard normal forms, where first normal is a minimal requirement.

First normal form enforces these criteria:

Eliminate repeating groups in individual tables.

Create a separate table for each set of related data.

Identify each set of related data with a primary key.

Wrong Example

The following table does not respect the 1NF norm, because the phone number column contains multiple values.

ID | First_Name | Last_Name | Phone number
1 | foo | bar | 555-2334-3234, 134-34454-0345
2 | toto | zoo | 666-2334-3234, 13-34454-0345

The following version respects the 1NF norm.

ID | First_Name | Last_Name | Phone_number1 | Phone_number2
1 | foo | bar | 555-2334-3234 | 134-34454-0345
2 | toto | zoo | 666-2334-3234 | 13-34454-0345

But this design does not work with users who have 3 phone numbers.

A better design is to separate the phone number from the custom table

Customer_ID | First_Name | Last_Name
1 | foo | bar
2 | toto | zoo

Phone_ID | Customer_ID | Phone_number
1 | 1 | 555-2334-3234
2 | 1 | 134-34454-0345
3 | 2 | 666-2334-3234
4 | 2 | 13-34454-0345

The custom name use Customer_ID to form a one to many relation between customer table and phone number table.

But we can't use Customer ID as primary key, Because it's not unique in the cloumn anymore.

Réunion du 26 Octobre 2017

Personnes présentes

CD

YM

Mathieu Eglinger

Céline Moret

Léa Cheng

Ordre du jour :

Storages

OGM/MOT

Demo

présentation disponible sur M:/02_DST/04_UTEC/06_UTEC/Projets/En cours/NoE/presentations/InternalMeetings/20171026_QSI–NoE_Interactions.pptx

Résumé

Storage

CD a présenté le travail qu'il a produit à partir les différents fichiers Excels du QSI concernant les stockages à BIOASTER.
Mauvaise nouvelle : les fichiers Excel ne seront plus renseignés, Tatiana ayant fait une base MS Access de tout ça…
Il a insisté sur le fait que plus on avait de sources, plus le potentiel d'erreurs était important.
Il a expliqué en quoi un fichier CSV est plus facilement manipulable qu'un fichier xlsx.
Selon ME les storages mutualisés des laboratoires sont tous partagés entre UTEC01/04 et 05. Par contre dans les pièce de stockage on ne peut pas savoir.
TODO :

demander le nom des stockages MOT (se trouvent en L1.10 et L4.1 d'après ME)

GMOs/MOTs

YM a présenté ce qui a été fait à partir des fichiers fournis par Céline Moret.
Les erreurs recensées ont été discutées.
TODO :

ajouter le projet/wp à chaque demande/agrément OGM. L'info se trouve dans le fichier suivi_dossier_OGM.xlsx colonne “sujet”. Le fichier est sur M. –> un OGM ne pourra pas être rajouté s'il n'est pas dans le bon WP.

ajouter les dates suivantes à chaque demande/agrément OGM :

date d'envoi

date d'accusé réception de La Poste

date d'autorisation (+45/90 jours après accusé réception pour les agréments et tout de suite pour les déclaration, cas à clarifier par mail avec ME)

date de péremption (+ 5 ans, a clarifier par mail avec ME)

ajouter les dates suivantes à chaque MOT :

date d'envoi

date d'autorisation

date de péremption

Démonstration

NoE a été introduit à la QSI.
Public ravi et impressionné.
Le design leur plait.
Gros effet “quantité tube en CSS”.

Questions/Remarques :

doit-on laisser le filtrage du BSL en fonction du labo physique dans lequel se trouve le frigo ou doit-on partir du fait qu'un échantillon P3 pourra être dans un frigo dans un labo P1 car il sera forcément bien conditionné ?

En version anglaise, l'affichage des dates est parfois à l'envers, parfois non. A vérifier.

Pour un échantillon humain, le statut sérologique de l'échantillon est obligatoire –> a rajouter en dynamic field

le service QSI est fortement interessé par la possibilité d'avoir des formulaires d'ajout pour les OGMs/MOTs/Stockage au lieu de passer par plein de fichier Excels ou une base MS Access.

Part 3: Services

In part 3, we scale our application and enable load-balancing. To do this, we must go one level up in the hierarchy of a distributed application: the service.

Stack Services (you are here) Container (covered in part 2)

About services

In a distributed application, different pieces of the app are called “services”. For example, if you imagine a video sharing site, it probably includes a service for storing application data in a database, a service for video transcoding in the background after a user uploads something, a service for the front-end, and so on.

Services are really just “containers in production.” A service only runs one image, but it codifies the way that image runs—what ports it should use, how many replicas of the container should run so the service has the capacity it needs, and so on. Scaling a service changes the number of container instances running that piece of software, assigning more computing resources to the service in the process.

Luckily it’s very easy to define, run, and scale services with the Docker platform – just write a docker-compose.yml file.

docker-compose.yml

A docker-compose.yml file is a YAML file that defines how Docker containers should behave in production.

Save this file as docker-compose.yml wherever you want. Be sure you have pushed the image you created in Part 2 to a registry, and update this .yml by replacing username/repo:tag with your image details. The following example is based on my settings

version: "3"
services:
  pengfeiweb:
  #the name of the service
    image: liupengfei99/test:v1
    deploy:
      replicas: 5
      resources:
        limits:
          cpus: "0.1"
          memory: 50M
      restart_policy:
        condition: on-failure
    ports:
      - "4000:80"
    networks:
      - webnet
networks:
  webnet:

The above docker-compose.yml file tells Docker to do the following:

Pull the image we uploaded in step 2 from the registry.

Run 5 instances of that image as a service called the “web”, limiting each one to use, at most, 10% of a single core of CPU time (this could also be e.g. “1.5” to mean 1 and a half core for each), and 50MB of RAM.

Immediately restart containers if one fails.

Map port 4000 on the host to web’s port 80.

Instruct web’s containers to share port 80 via a load-balanced network called webnet. (Internally, the containers themselves publish to web’s port 80 at an ephemeral port.)

Define the website network with the default settings (which is a load-balanced overlay network).

Run your new load-balanced app

Before we can use the docker stack deploy command we first run:

docker swarm init

# Note: We get into the meaning of that command in part 4. If you don’t run docker swarm init you get an error that “this node is not a swarm manager.” 

Now let’s run it. You need to give your app a name. Here, it is set to dockerlab:

docker stack deploy -c docker-compose.yml dockerlab
# The above command will run a single service stack. This single service stack is running 5 container instances of our deployed image on one host. Let’s investigate.

# If all works fine, you should see
Creating network dockerlab_webnet
Creating service dockerlab_pengfeiweb

# Get the service ID for the one service in our application:
$ docker service ls

ID                  NAME                   MODE                REPLICAS            IMAGE                  PORTS
4bjr3jvhzp02        dockerlab_pengfeiweb   replicated          5/5                 liupengfei99/test:v1   *:4000->80/tcp

# Alternatively, you can run docker stack services, followed by the name of your stack. The following example command lets you view all services associated with the dockerlab stack:
$ docker stack services dockerlab

# A single container running in service is called a task. Tasks are given unique IDs that numerically increment, up to the number of replicas you defined in docker-compose.yml. List the tasks for your service:

$ docker service ps dockerlab_pengfeiweb
ID                  NAME                     IMAGE                  NODE                    DESIRED STATE       CURRENT STATE           ERROR               PORTS
sdh1ws0hafcg        dockerlab_pengfeiweb.1   liupengfei99/test:v1   localhost.localdomain   Running             Running 7 minutes ago                       
yg6hnito06e1        dockerlab_pengfeiweb.2   liupengfei99/test:v1   localhost.localdomain   Running             Running 7 minutes ago                       

# Tasks also show up if you just list all the containers on your system, though that is not filtered by service:

$ docker container ls -q

Scale the app

You can scale the app by changing the replicas value in docker-compose.yml, saving the change, and re-run the docker stack deploy.

Docker performs an in-place update, no need to tear the stack down first or kill any containers.

Take down the app and the swarm

# Take the app down
docker stack rm dockerlab

# Take down the swarn
docker swarm leave --force

Recap

docker stack ls                                            # List stacks or apps
docker stack deploy -c <composefile> <appname>  # Run the specified Compose file
docker service ls                 # List running services associated with an app
docker service ps <service>                  # List tasks associated with an app
docker inspect <task or container>                   # Inspect task or container
docker container ls -q                                      # List container IDs
docker stack rm <appname>                             # Tear down an application
docker swarm leave --force      # Take down a single node swarm from the manager

Apache2 common problems

No space left on device AH00023: Couldn't create the ssl-cache mutex.

Apache is basically saying “I want to start, but I need to write some things down before I can start, and I have nowhere to write them!” If this happens to you, check these items in order:

1. Check your disk space

2. Review filesystem quotas If your filesystem uses quotas, you might be reaching a quota limit rather than a disk space limit. Use repquota / to review your quotas on the root partition. If you’re at the limit, raise your quota or clear up some disk space. Apache logs are usually the culprit in these situations.

3. Clear out your active semaphores Semaphores? What the heck is a semaphore? Well, it’s actually an apparatus for conveying information by means of visual signals. But, when it comes to programming, semaphores are used for communicating between the active processes of a certain application. In the case of Apache, they’re used to communicate between the parent and child processes. If Apache can’t write these things down, then it can’t communicate properly with all of the processes it starts.

#stop apache
systemctl stop httpd
#show semaphores
ipcs -s
 
#create a clean script 
vim clean.sh
#!/bin/bash
 
for i in `ipcs --semaphores | grep apache | awk '{print $2}'` ;
do
ipcrm --semaphore-id $i;
done ;

if this is still not working you need to increase the semaphores spaces You need to tickle your kernel to do so.

vim /etc/sysctl.conf

#put the following lines
kernel.msgmni = 1024
kernel.sem = 250 256000 32 1024

#reload the conf file
sysctl -p

Install mariadb on centos7

MariaDB is a drop-in replacement for MySQL. It is easy to install, offers many speed and performance improvements, and is easy to integrate into most MySQL deployments. Answers for compatibility questions can be found at: MariaDB versus MySQL Compatibility. MariaDB offers more storage engines than MySQL, including Cassandra (NoSQL, in MariaDB Version 10), XtraDB (drop-in replacement for InnoDB), and OQGRAPH (in MariaDB Version 10).

Pre-Flight Check These instructions are intended for installing MariaDB on a single CentOS 7 node. I’ll be working from a Liquid Web Self Managed CentOS 7 server, and I’ll be logged in as root.

Install MySQL / MariaDB Installing MariaDB is as simple as running just one command:

yum -y install mariadb-server mariadb

And then start MySQL, now MariaDB:

systemctl start mariadb

Be sure that MySQL/MariaDB starts at boot:

systemctl enable mariadb

To check the status of MySQL/MariaDB:

systemctl status mariadb

To top MySQL/MariaDB:

systemctl stop mariadb

Check the installation with the command client:

mysql
Welcome to the MariaDB monitor.  Commands end with ; or \g.
Your MariaDB connection id is 2
Server version: 5.5.56-MariaDB MariaDB Server

Copyright (c) 2000, 2017, Oracle, MariaDB Corporation Ab and others.

Type 'help;' or '\h' for help. Type '\c' to clear the current input statement.

MariaDB [(none)]> exit
Bye

Configuration post installation

As you see from above, by default, the installation doesn’t assign any password to MySQL root account.

To set the mysql root user password and perform other security configuration on the database, execute the mysql_secure_installation script as shown below.

If you use yum to install the mariadb, the mysql_secure_installation script should be in your path. So just type mysql_secure_installation

Follow the instruction, the mariadb is configured.

JDBC driver

https://mariadb.com/kb/en/library/about-mariadb-connector-j/

Reset root password for MySql or MariaDB

Forgetting passwords happens to the best of us. If you forget or lose the root password to your MySQL or MariaDB database, you can still gain access and reset the password if you have access to the server and a sudo-enabled user account.

This tutorial will cover how to reset the root password for older and newer versions of MySQL and MariaDB.

Prerequisites

Access to the Linux server running MySQL or MariaDB with a sudo user.

Step 1. check version

Based on different version, you will need different commands to reset the password. So you need to know which version of your server is

mysql --version

Step2. Stop the server

#for mysql
sudo systemctl stop mysql

#for mariadb
sudo systemctl stop mariadb

Step3. Restarting the server without permission checking

If you run MySQL and MariaDB without loading information about user privileges, it will allow you to access the database command line with root privileges without providing a password. This will allow you to gain access to the database without knowing it.

To do this, you need to stop the database from loading the grant tables, which store user privilege information. Because this is a bit of a security risk, you should also skip networking as well to prevent other clients from connecting.

Start the database without loading the grant tables or enabling networking:

# start server
sudo mysqld_safe --skip-grant-tables --skip-networking &

# connect to the server
mysql -u root

# if you can't start mysqld in safe mode, do the following command
systemctl set-environment MYSQLD_OPTS="--skip-grant-tables"
systemctl start mysqld

Step4. change the password

One simple way to change the root password for modern versions of MySQL is using the ALTER USER command. However, this command won't work right now because the grant tables aren't loaded.

Let's tell the database server to reload the grant tables by issuing the FLUSH PRIVILEGES command.

mysql > FLUSH PRIVILEGES;

For MySQL 5.7.6 and newer as well as MariaDB 10.1.20 and newer, use the following command.

mysql > ALTER USER 'root'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'new_password';

For MySQL 5.7.5 and older as well as MariaDB 10.1.20 and older, use:

mysql > SET PASSWORD FOR 'root'@'localhost' = PASSWORD('new_password');

Make sure to replace new_password with your new password of choice.

Note: If the ALTER USER command doesn't work, it's usually indicative of a bigger problem. However, you can try UPDATE … SET to reset the root password instead

UPDATE mysql.user SET authentication_string = PASSWORD('new_password') WHERE User = 'root' AND Host = 'localhost';

Remember to reload the grant tables after this.

Step 5. stop the server and restart it normally

First, identify the mysqld_safe process id

> ps aux | grep mysqld_safe
root     20550  0.0  0.0 113260  1600 pts/0    T    09:40   0:00 /bin/sh /bin/mysqld_safe --skip-grant-tables --skip-networking
root     20877  0.0  0.0 112660   980 pts/0    S+   09:50   0:00 grep --color=auto mysqld_safe

The process id is 20550

kill -9 20550

To bring the background process to foreground use fg

Restart the server

# If you modified the mysqld_opts to login without password, you need to reset it
systemctl unset-environment MYSQLD_OPTS

#for mysql
sudo systemctl start mysql

#for mariadb
sudo systemctl start mariadb

# connect to the server as root
mysql -u root -p

Ici nous vous proposons d'indiquer les différents use cases de NoE.

Scenarii reçus de la NeT

UTEC01

cas 1 (Ces échantillons ne peuvent pas être utilisés dans le cadre d’un autre projet et doivent être détruits à la fin du projet. Catégorie de transport catégorie B.) :

150 échantillons 1,5 mL de Lavages Broncho-alvéolaires (LBA) (1/patient) et 150 échantillons de 10 mL d’urines (1/patient) provenant de patients présentant une suspicion de pneumonie, dans le cadre du projet BA010WP4 dont BIOASTER est promoteur.

Les tubes arrivent étiquetés selon la règle définie par l’IRC BIOASTER dans le protocole.

Ces échantillons sont aliquotés à réception : 3 aliquots par patient de 500µL de LBA et 10 aliquots d’urine de 1 mL par patient.

cas 2 (Ces isolats doivent être rattachés au bon patient et au bon prélèvement. Ces isolats pourraient être utilisés dans le cadre d’un autre projet):

640 isolats cliniques bactériens isolés à partir des LBA ou des urines provenant des patients inclus dans l’étude décrite dans le cas n°1.

Toutes ces souches sont conservées en glycérol, leur profil de résistance aux antibiotiques a été établi ainsi que leur CMI et également quantifiées en CFU/mL. Il s’agit de :

190 isolats de Pseudomonas aeruginosa

120 isolats de Staphilococcus aureus

70 isolats d’Escherichia coli

170 isolats d’Haemophilus influenza

90 isolats Acinetobacter baumannii

cas 3 : Ce cas concerne l’extraction des ADN des échantillons collectés dans le cadre du cas n°1, à savoir :

150 extractions d’ADN réalisées à partir des 150 LBA

150 extractions d’ADN réalisées à partir des 150 urines

Pour chaque extraction, 5 aliquots de 120 ng sont conservés, soit 5 par patient et par urine et par LBA, soit 1500 aliquots conservés et saisis/importés dans le LIMS.

Ces échantillons doivent être rattachés au bon patient et au bon prélèvement d’origine.

cas 4 :

Acquisition d’une souche commerciale provenant de DSMZ

Dénomination : Staphylococcus aureus

N° DSMZ: 11110

Autre designation: ATCC 6341

1 ampoule lyophilisée reçue correspondant à la génération 0.

L’ampoule est mise en culture 2 mois plus tard et une génération est créée : 100 congelats sont préparés et congelés à -80°C

5 ans plus tard, une nouvelle génération est créée à partir du dernier congelat de la génération 1.

100 congelats sont générés.

cas 5 : J’ai mis en culture des échantillons LBA et urine collectés dans le cas n°1. Des bactéries ont poussé sur boîte mais toutes n’ont pas pu être identifiées. Je prépare tout de même des congelats des bactéries isolées afin de les caractériser ultérieurement. Au moment où je saisis dans le LIMS, je ne connais pas son genre et son espèce.

cas 6 :

Réception de 25 échantillons de PBMCs isolés à partir de plasma EDTA provenant de patients neutropéniques (groupe +) et de patients sains (groupe -) dans le cadre du projet BA025WP7. Conservation en azote liquide -196°C.

BIOASTER n’est pas promoteur de l’étude et le technicien à réception de ces échantillons n’a aucune idée sur le caractère mutualisable ou pas de ces échantillons.

cas 7 :

Réception de 20 biopsies de peau humaine, 20 gel strips cutanés et 20 écouvillons cutanés, prélevées sur le dos de sujets acnéiques.

Les biopsies sont conservées en azote liquide -196°C, les autres à -80°C

Des lymphocytes T sont isolés à partir des biopsies

cas 8:

Je reçois un échantillon d’eau provenant de la Seine afin de recherche des amibes.

J’identifie Amoeba proteus que je congèle à -80°C.

UTEC02

Je dois créer 210 échantillons de sérum de patient HBV pour le projet NAT-B qui servira à plusieurs UTEC (UTEC02, 03). Au sein de l’UTEC02 je vais extraire les ADN viraux à partir desquels je vais préparer mes librairies de séquençage.

Je dois créer 115 échantillons de souches bactériennes isolées pour la prestation Biocollection à partir desquels je vais extraire les ADNg qui serviront ensuite à préparer mes librairies de séquençage.

Je dois créer 150 échantillons de sang total prélevé dans des tubes PAXgene à partir desquels je vais réaliser des extractions d’ARN total qui me serviront par la suite pour préparer des librairies.

Je dois créer 120 échantillons de feces pour une prestation à partir desquels je vais extraire les ADNg des bactéries présentes dans chacun des échantillons qui me serviront par la suite pour préparer mes librairies.

Je dois créer 30 échantillons de caecums pour le projet Prochick à partir desquels je vais réaliser les dissections avant d’extraire les ADNg des bactéries présentes dans chacun des échantillons qui me serviront par la suite pour préparer mes librairies.

Je dois créer 10 échantillons de mélange de bactéries cultivées en fermenteur de laboratoire à partir desquels je vais extraire les ADNg des bactéries présentes dans chacun des échantillons qui me serviront par la suite pour préparer mes librairies.

UTEC03 Paris

Des tubes de sang, qualifiés ou non qualifiés, en provenance de l EFS Saint-Antoine, de 1- 4 tubes, de 5 à 20ml, contenant un anticoagulant (Na-Heparin, EDTA, citrate) ayant une identification EFS

Nous recevons souvent plusieurs échantillons à enregistrés en même temps

Des tubes de sang en provenance de Cochin, 4 tubes de patients HBV positif pour l’étude ABL E0086, avec une identification Cochin

Tube de sang de souris, Swiss ou Balb, de 1-4ml, de Janvier Labs

Du sang et organes de souris (poumon, rate, foie, muscle), sain, infecté ou injecté avec adjuvant/vaccin, avec un poids déterminé, de souris conventionnelle ou de souris humanisés

Des tubes de lignées cellulaires en provenance de l ATCC ou d’un autre labo, avec le n° de passage, ayant une identification EFS

Une poche de buffy coat de 300-400ml en anticoagulant (ACD) en provenance de l EFS de Rungis, ayant une identification EFS

Des poches de plasma de 20-100ml en anticoagulant en provenance de l EFS de Rungis, ayant une identification EFS

Des protéines synthétisées par l UTEC04 ou autres sociétés, avec volume et concentration déterminés

Des PBMC issus de sang d’un donneur/patient de l EFS ou de Cochin, on enregistre alors le nombre de tubes, la concentration cellulaire et l ID d’origine

UTEC03 Lyon

Rien

UTEC04 et UTEC05

Souche bactérienne commerciale Anaerotruncus colihominis JM4-15, DSM 28734 ; origine : mouse intestine ; conservation dans 20% glycérol à -80°C

Souche bactérienne Lactobacillus murinus 313 isolée à partir de fèces de souris C57BL/6 WT SOPF ; conservation dans 20% glycérol à -80°C

ADN extrait à partir d’une souche bactérienne Clostridium ASF356 isolée à partir de contenu caecal de souris C57BL/6 WT Gnotobiotic ASF ; conservation à -20°C

Ganglions mésentériques prélevés sur souris C57BL/6 WT Germ-free ; conservation à 4°C

Colon conservé en paraffine, prélevé sur souris C57BL/6 WT Gnotobiotic GnotoMice ; conservation à -20°C

Fémur conservé en éthanol 80%, prélevé sur souris C57BL/6 WT SOPF ; conservation à 4°C

Je crée une banque d’hybridomes de 300 clones. Elle a été générée à partir de la fusion des splénocytes de souris immunisées avec un antigène X et une lignée immortalisée. Chaque clone produit un anticorps mais ses spécificités ne sont pas encore déterminées

Je crée une souche génétiquement modifiée à partir d’une souche bactérienne commerciale

Je crée une lignée cellulaire de production d’une protéine à partir d’une lignée cellulaire commerciale stablement transfectée avec un plasmide contenant la protéine exprimée

Je rentre 10 ampoules de cellules CHO congelées : Bioentity – mammal (chinese hamster). Sample type – cell line (immortalized ovary cells)

UTEC07

Rien

CODIRA

Je rentre une souche commerciale (ATCC) d’E. Coli

Je rentre une souche envoyée par un partenaire (et non diffusable). Souvent elles sont répertoriées avec des noms propres à la classif du partenaire, puis la nôtre qui est différente…

Je rentre une souche isolée à partir d’un swab prélevé au niveau de l’aisselle du patient n°X de la campagne MDRO. La souche isolée a été identifiée (nom) par l’équipe avant congélation (nom actuel : MDRO_X_numéro d’incrémentation de la souche isolée).

Je rentre une souche isolée à partir d’un swab prélevé au niveau du vagin de la patiente n°X de la campagne GBS. La souche isolée a été identifiée (nom) par l’équipe avant congélation (nom actuel : GBS_X_numéro d’incrémentation de la souche isolée).

Screen

Linux Screen allows you to:

Use multiple shell windows from a single SSH session.

Keep a shell active even through network disruptions.

Disconnect and re-connect to a shell sessions from multiple locations.

Run a long running process without maintaining an active shell session.

Install screen

There is great chance your linux already have screen installed

#check if you have screen or not
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 pliu]$ which screen
#if you see this, it's installed
/bin/screen

#otherwise
sudo yum install screen

Use screen

#open a screen
> screen

Once you are inside a screen you can type any command as you are in a normal shell, to give command to screen. You need to use<color #ed1c24> Ctrl-a</color> then options. Screen works like vim, it has a mode command. By typing ctrl-a you enter to command mode.

Creating a new window

Ctrl-a c

This will create a new window for you with your default prompt. Your old window is still active.

Switching Between windows

Ctrl-a n

Screen allows you to move forward and back. In the example above, you could use “Ctrl-a “n” to get back to top. This command switches you to the next window.

The windows work like a carousel and will loop back around to your first window.

You can create several windows and toggle through them with “Ctrl-a” “n” for the next window or “Ctrl-a” “p” for the previous window.

Each process will keep running until you kill that window.

Detaching from screen

Ctrl-a d

Detaching is the most powerful part of screen. Screen allows you to detach from a window and reattach later.

If your network connection fails, screen will automatically detach your session!

You can detach from the window using “Ctrl-a” “d”.

This will drop you into your shell.

All screen windows are still there and you can re-attach to them later.

This is great when you are using rsync for server migration.

Reattach to screen

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 pliu]$ screen -r

This will re-attach to your screen.

However, if you have multiple screens you may get this:

$ screen -r
There are several suitable screens on:
31917.pts-5.office      (Detached)
31844.pts-0.office      (Detached)
Type "screen [-d] -r [pid.]tty.host" to resume one of them.
If you get this, just specify the screen you want.

$ screen -r  31844.pts-0.office

Beware, ctrl-a c create a new window inside one screen. One screen can have multiple windows.

List all screen session

The screen -list depends on user session, see the following example

[root@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]# screen -list
No Sockets found in /var/run/screen/S-root.

[root@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]# su hadoop
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ screen -list
There is a screen on:
	16558.$name	(Attached)
1 Socket in /var/run/screen/S-hadoop.

Attaching an attached screen

screen -x 16558.$name

Scoll up and down to your screen

Use ctrl+a then [ to enter to copy mode.

Once you are in copy mode, you can scoll up and down.

Logging your screen output

It's important to keep track of what I do on a server. Fortunately, screen makes this easy.

Using “Ctrl-a” “H”, creates a running log of the session.

Screen will keep appending data to the file through multiple sessions. Using the log function is very useful for capturing what you have done, especially if you are making a lot of changes. If something goes awry, you can look back through your logs.

With “Ctrl-a H” the screen will write the output into the default log file which is defined in the default screen conf file

To write the output in your own way

cd /tmp
vim /tmp/screen.conf

#put the following lines
logfile screen_test.log
logfile flush 1
log on
logtstamp after 1
logtstamp string "[ %t: %Y-%m-%d %c:%s ]\012"
logtstamp on

#run the screen with your custom conf
screen -c ./tmp/screen.conf -dmSL 'screen_test' /tmp/helloworld.sh

# -dm means creates a new session with mode "detached"
# -S means specify the session name
# -L tells screen to turn on automatic output logging for the windows

# so the above script run screen with a conf file screen.conf, with session name 'screen_test' and runs 
# the shell helloworld.sh in the screen session.
 

To make it easier, we can build a script to run the above automatically.

#!/bin/bash
# name of the screen session can't be empty
if [[ $1 == "" ]]; then
    echo "Usage: $0 name";
    exit 1;
fi
# get the screen session name
name=$1
# define screen output log path
# make sure the runner of the script has the right to write in it
path="/tmp/log";
# define the screen log config
config="logfile ${path}/${name}.log
logfile flush 1
log on
logtstamp after 1
logtstamp string \"[ %t: %Y-%m-%d %c:%s ]\012\"
logtstamp on";
# write the log config to a temporal file
echo "$config" > /tmp/log.conf
# run screen with log config 
screen -c /tmp/log.conf -dmSL $name 
# remove the temporal config file
#rm /tmp/log.conf

The above script takes an argument as session name, and creates a detached screen session.

Sharing a screen session with another user

Open a screen with user1

Enable mutli-user mode ([user1@ tmp]$ Ctrl-a :multiuser on)

Add the desired user(s) ([user1@ tmp]$ Ctrl-a :acladd user2)

User2 connect to screen of user1 ([user2@ ~]$ screen -x user1/shared)

If you receive a error message ( Must run suid root for multiuser support.) you need to log out and do the following commands

[user1@ ~]$ su -
Password: 
[root@ ~]# chmod u+s $(which screen)
[root@ ~]# chmod 755 /var/run/screen
[root@ ~]# rm -fr /var/run/screen/*
[root@ ~]# exit
logout

Ps: making the screen command suid root is a security issue (otherwise, wouldn't it already have been set this way). So, you may be better off making a third shared account which both users can log into to share a screen session with.

Flume agent seq generator source, mem channel, hdfs sink

In this tutorial, we will build a flume agent which fetch data from a Sequence generator source. The sequence generator source is for test purpose only, don't use it in a production environment.

Configure flume

As we said, this flume agent has a seq source, a mem channel and a hdfs sink

Sequence Generator Source

It is the source that generates the events continuously. It maintains a counter that starts from 0 and increments by 1. It is used for testing purpose. While configuring this source, you must provide values to the following properties:

Channels

Source type − seq

Channel

We are using the memory channel. To configure the memory channel, you must provide value to the type of the channel. Given below are the list of properties that you need to supply while configuring the memory channel:

type − It holds the type of the channel. In our example the type is MemChannel.

Capacity − It is the maximum number of events stored in the channel. Its default value is 100. (optional)

TransactionCapacity − It is the maximum number of events the channel accepts or sends. Its default is 100. (optional).

Sink

In this tutorial, we use an HDFS Sink which writes data into the HDFS. To configure this sink, you must provide the following details:

Channel

type : hdfs

hdfs.path : the path of the directory in HDFS where data is to be stored.

And we can provide some optional values based on the scenario. Given below are the optional properties of the HDFS sink that we are configuring in our application.

fileType : This is the required file format of our HDFS file. SequenceFile, DataStream and CompressedStream are the three types available with this stream. In our example, we are using the DataStream.

writeFormat: Could be either text or writable.

batchSize: It is the number of events written to a file before it is flushed into the HDFS. Its default value is 100.

rollsize: It is the file size to trigger a roll. Its default value is 100.

rollCount: It is the number of events written into the file before it is rolled. Its default value is 10.

Full flume agent conf

We put the following config into “/opt/flume/flume-1.9.0/conf/agent-example/seq-gen.conf”. You can put it wherever you want, we do it like this just as a good practice.

# In this agent, we use a Sequence generator as the source, a memory channel, and hdfs as the sink

# Naming the components on the current agent 

SeqGenAgent.sources = SeqSource   
SeqGenAgent.channels = MemChannel 
SeqGenAgent.sinks = HDFS 
 
# Describing/Configuring the source 
SeqGenAgent.sources.SeqSource.type = seq
  
# Describing/Configuring the sink
# sink writes data into the HDFS. To configure this sink, you must provide the following details:
SeqGenAgent.sinks.HDFS.type = hdfs 
SeqGenAgent.sinks.HDFS.hdfs.path = hdfs://localhost:9000/tmp/seqgen_data
SeqGenAgent.sinks.HDFS.hdfs.filePrefix = log 
SeqGenAgent.sinks.HDFS.hdfs.rollInterval = 0
SeqGenAgent.sinks.HDFS.hdfs.rollCount = 10000
SeqGenAgent.sinks.HDFS.hdfs.fileType = DataStream 
 
# Describing/Configuring the channel 
SeqGenAgent.channels.MemChannel.type = memory 
SeqGenAgent.channels.MemChannel.capacity = 1000 
SeqGenAgent.channels.MemChannel.transactionCapacity = 100 
 
# Binding the source and sink to the channel 
SeqGenAgent.sources.SeqSource.channels = MemChannel
SeqGenAgent.sinks.HDFS.channel = MemChannel 

Now we need to run this flume agent

# the full command for launching the flume agent
flume-ng agent -f seq-gen.conf -n SeqGenAgent -Dflume.root.logger=INFO,console

# -f indicates where is the flume agent conf file
# -n indicates the flume agent name in the conf file
# -Dflume.root.logger=INFO,console means the log level is INFO, the output is redirected to console.

Kafka installation and configuration

Publish-subscribe messaging system

In the publish-subscribe system, messages are persisted in a topic. Unlike point-to-point system, consumers can subscribe to one or more topic and consume all the messages in that topic. In the Publish-Subscribe system, message producers are called publishers and message consumers are called subscribers. A real-life example is Dish TV, which publishes different channels like sports, movies, music, etc., and anyone can subscribe to their own set of channels and get them whenever their subscribed channels are available.

What is Kafka?

Apache Kafka is a distributed publish-subscribe messaging system and a robust queue that can handle a high volume of data and enables you to pass messages from one end-point to another. Kafka is suitable for both offline and online message consumption. Kafka messages are persisted on the disk and replicated within the cluster to prevent data loss. Kafka is built on top of the ZooKeeper synchronization service. It integrates very well with Apache Storm and Spark for real-time streaming data analysis

Kafka use case

Metrics - Kafka is often used for operational monitoring data. This involves aggregating statistics from distributed applications to produce centralized feeds of operational data.

Log Aggregation Solution - Kafka can be used across an organization to collect logs from multiple services and make them available in a standard format to multiple consumers.

Stream Processing - Popular frameworks such as Storm and Spark Streaming read data from a topic, processes it, and write processed data to a new topic where it becomes available for users and applications. Kafka’s strong durability is also very useful in the context of stream processing.

Kafka key concepts

Broker → In a kafka cluster, we may have one or many server. The server is called broker

Topic → Each message in kafka must has a category, we call the category a Topic

Partition → Each Topic can have one or more Partitions.

Producer → A program or process which can send messages to Broker

Consumer → A program or process which read messages from Broker

Consumer group → Each consumer belongs to a consumer group. When you create a consumer, you can specify consumer group name, otherwise kafka will assign a default group name.

Install kafka

A critical dependency of Apache Kafka is Apache Zookeeper, which is a distributed configuration and synchronization service. Zookeeper serves as the coordination interface between the Kafka brokers and consumers. The Kafka servers share information via a Zookeeper cluster. Kafka stores basic metadata in Zookeeper such as information about topics, brokers, consumer offsets (queue readers) and so on.

Since all the critical information is stored in the Zookeeper and it normally replicates this data across its ensemble, failure of Kafka broker / Zookeeper does not affect the state of the Kafka cluster. Kafka will restore the state, once the Zookeeper restarts. This gives zero downtime for Kafka. The leader election between the Kafka broker is also done by using Zookeeper in the event of leader failure.

To learn more about ZooKeeper, Zookeeper

Download the kafka binary from http://kafka.apache.org/downloads.html

Then place the binary in your server

mkdir /opt/kafka

cd /opt/kafka

tar -xzvf  kafka_2.11-1.0.0.tgz 

cd /opt/kafka/kafka_2.11-1.0.0/config

vim server.properties

change the default config to adapter your environment

#default
broker.id=0
zookeeper.connect=localhost:2181

#in my environment
zookeeper.connect=hadoop-nn.pengfei.org:2181,hadoop-dn1.pengfei.org:2181,hadoop-dn2.pengfei.org:2181
broker.id=1 (2,3 in other two machines)

The above config is the minimun config to run kafka, you may need to dig more.

if your zookeeper cluster already running or controlled by zookeeper, you don't need to chage the config of /opt/kafka/kafka_2.11-1.0.0/config/zookeeper.properties

if you want to use kafka to control the zookeeper daemon, you need to edit the zookeeper.properties

Here is an example

# the directory where the snapshot is stored.
dataDir=/opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/data
# the port at which the clients will connect
clientPort=2181
# disable the per-ip limit on the number of connections since this is a non-production config
maxClientCnxns=0

# The number of milliseconds of each tick
tickTime=2000

# The number of ticks that the initial synchronization phase can take
initLimit=10

# The number of ticks that can pass between 
# sending a request and getting an acknowledgement
syncLimit=5

#zoo servers
server.1=hadoop-nn.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.2=hadoop-dn1.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.3=hadoop-dn2.pengfei.org:2888:3888

It's the same as the zoo.cfg in zookeeper

# The number of milliseconds of each tick
tickTime=2000
# The number of ticks that the initial 
# synchronization phase can take
#initLimit=10
initLimit=5
# The number of ticks that can pass between 
# sending a request and getting an acknowledgement
#syncLimit=5
syncLimit=5
# the directory where the snapshot is stored.
# do not use /tmp for storage, /tmp here is just 
# example sakes.
dataDir=/opt/zookeeper/zookeeper-3.4.10/data
# the port at which the clients will connect
clientPort=2181
# the maximum number of client connections.
# increase this if you need to handle more clients
#maxClientCnxns=60
#
# Be sure to read the maintenance section of the 
# administrator guide before turning on autopurge.
#
# http://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/current/zookeeperAdmin.html#sc_maintenance
#
# The number of snapshots to retain in dataDir
#autopurge.snapRetainCount=3
# Purge task interval in hours
# Set to "0" to disable auto purge feature
#autopurge.purgeInterval=1

server.1=hadoop-nn.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.2=hadoop-dn1.pengfei.org:2888:3888
server.3=hadoop-dn2.pengfei.org:2888:3888

To run the zookeeper daemon in kafak

cd /opt/kafka/kafka_2.11-1.0.0
sh bin/zookeeper-server-start.sh config/zookeeper.properties

Run the kafka server (with one broker)

sh bin/kafka-server-start.sh config/server.properties

you can run multi broker on the same server

#run three broker on the same server
sh bin/kafka-server-start.sh /config/server1.properties
sh bin/kafka-server-start.sh /config/server2.properties
sh bin/kafka-server-start.sh /config/server3.properties

#you need to make sure the "broker.id", "port number" and "log file path" are unique in each
#server.properties to avoid conflict

##########server1.properties
# The id of the broker. This must be set to a unique integer for each broker.
broker.id=1
# The port the socket server listens on
port=9093
# A comma seperated list of directories under which to store log files
log.dirs=/tmp/kafka-logs-1

##########server2.properties
# The id of the broker. This must be set to a unique integer for each broker.
broker.id=2
# The port the socket server listens on
port=9094
# A comma seperated list of directories under which to store log files
log.dirs=/tmp/kafka-logs-2

Create topic in kafka

Create a topic with one partitions and three replication

#create a topic
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --create --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org --replication-factor 3 --partitions 1 --topic test-topic
Created topic "test-topic".

#check status of a topic
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --describe --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org --topic test-topic
Topic:test-topic	PartitionCount:1	ReplicationFactor:3	Configs:
	Topic: test-topic	Partition: 0	Leader: 2	Replicas: 2,3,1	Isr: 2,3,1

Create a topic with three partitions and three replication

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --create --zookeeper localhost:2181 --replication-factor 3 --partitions 3 --topic Hello-Kafka

Created topic "Hello-Kafka".

#get status of the topic
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --describe --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --topic Hello-Kafka
Topic:Hello-Kafka	PartitionCount:3	ReplicationFactor:3	Configs:
	Topic: Hello-Kafka	Partition: 0	Leader: 1	Replicas: 1,2,3	Isr: 1
	Topic: Hello-Kafka	Partition: 1	Leader: 2	Replicas: 2,3,1	Isr: 2,3,1
	Topic: Hello-Kafka	Partition: 2	Leader: 3	Replicas: 3,1,2	Isr: 3,1,2

List all topic in one broker

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --list --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181
Hello-Kafka
test-topic

Run producer and consummer by using kafka cli

Start producer to send messages

# In the broker-list, you could put one or more kafka brokers
# In this example, we use only one, the name of the broker is defined in server.properties  
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-console-producer.sh --broker-list hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:9092 --topic Hello-Kafka
#now you are in producer consol, all the text you enter below will be published in topic Hello-Kafka
>hello
>my first message
>my second message
>my third message

Start two consumers to receive messages

###in server hadoop-dn1.bioaster.org
hadoop@CCLinDataWHD02 bin]$ sh kafka-console-consumer.sh --zookeeper hadoop-dn1.bioaster.org:2181 --topic Hello-Kafka --from-beginning
Using the ConsoleConsumer with old consumer is deprecated and will be removed in a future major release. Consider using the new consumer by passing [bootstrap-server] instead of [zookeeper].
hello
my first message
my second message
my third message
my fouth message
my fifth message


###in server hadoop-dn2.bioaster.org
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD03-0 bin]$ sh kafka-console-consumer.sh --zookeeper hadoop-dn2.bioaster.org:2181 --topic Hello-Kafka --from-beginning
Using the ConsoleConsumer with old consumer is deprecated and will be removed in a future major release. Consider using the new consumer by passing [bootstrap-server] instead of [zookeeper].
hello
my third message
my first message
my second message
my fouth message
my fifth message


##You could notice, if your consumer connecter after many message has been published
##the order may not be correct. But the latest message will be correct

Basic topic operations

List all topics

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --list --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181
Hello-Kafka
test-topic

#show detail of topic test-topic
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --describe --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --topic test-topic
Topic:test-topic	PartitionCount:1	ReplicationFactor:3	Configs:
	Topic: test-topic	Partition: 0	Leader: 2	Replicas: 2,3,1	Isr: 2,1,3

#we know that it has one partition and 3 replicas

#Now we want to change the partition from one to two
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --alter --topic test-topic --partitions 2
WARNING: If partitions are increased for a topic that has a key, the partition logic or ordering of the messages will be affected
Adding partitions succeeded!

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --describe --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --topic test-topic
Topic:test-topic	PartitionCount:2	ReplicationFactor:3	Configs:
	Topic: test-topic	Partition: 0	Leader: 2	Replicas: 2,3,1	Isr: 2,1,3
	Topic: test-topic	Partition: 1	Leader: 3	Replicas: 3,2,1	Isr: 3,2,1

Delet a topic

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181 --delete --topic test-topic
Topic test-topic is marked for deletion.
Note: This will have no impact if delete.topic.enable is not set to true.
[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 bin]$ sh kafka-topics.sh --list --zookeeper hadoop-nn.bioaster.org:2181
Hello-Kafka

Lesson03: Advance configuration

3.1 broker configuration

The main config file of a Kafka broker is on the server.properties file. The default config is enough to run a standalone Kafka broker as a test server. But I still want to highlight some key configuration attributes.

【broker.id】
每个broker都必须自己设置的一个唯一id，可以在0~255之间. A good guideline is to set this value 
to something intrinsic to the host. For example, if your hostnames contain a unique number (such as host1.example.com , host2.example.com , etc.), that is a good choice for the broker.id value.

【log.dirs】
这个极为重要，kafka的所有数据就是写入这个目录下的磁盘文件中的，如果说机器上有多块物理硬盘，
那么可以把多个目录挂载到不同的物理硬盘上，然后这里可以设置多个目录，这样kafka可以数据分散
到多块物理硬盘，多个硬盘的磁头可以并行写，这样可以提升吞吐量。ps：多个目录用英文逗号分隔. 
If more than one path is specified(e.g. log.dirs=path1,path2), the broker will store 
partitions on them in a “least-used” fashion with one partition’s log segments stored 
within the same path. Note that the broker will place a new partition in the path that 
has the least number of partitions currently stored in it, not the least amount of disk 
space used in the following situations

【zookeeper.connect】
Kafka utilizes Zookeeper for storing metadata information about the brokers, topics,
and partitions. This configures kafka to connect zookeeper. The default configuration 
is localhost:2181. This will create all required znode of kafka under the root of zk. 
If you want to specify a special path for storing all the kafka data, you can use  
localhost:2181/path, If a chroot path is specified and does not exist, it will be created 
by the broker when it starts up. 

This can be useful when you have one zk cluster for multiple kafka clusters.

【Listeners】
broker监听客户端发起请求的ip,端口号，默认是9092. It will get the value returned from ** java.net.InetAddress.getCanonicalHostName() if not configured**. The port number can be set to any available port by changing the port configuration parameter. Keep in mind that if a port lower than 1024 is chosen, Kafka must be started as root. Running Kafka as root is not a recommended configuration.

【num.network.threads】The number of threads that the server uses for **receiving requests** from the network and sending responses to the network .默认值为3
【num.io.threads】The number of threads that the server uses for **processing requests**, which may include disk I/O. 默认值为8, 这就是上一篇我们在网络架构上提到的processor和处理线程池的线程数目。这两个参数就是Kafka集群性能的关键参数了

【unclean.leader.election.enable】
默认是false，意思就是只能选举ISR列表里的follower成为新的leader，1.0版本后才设为false，之前都是true，允许非ISR列表的follower选举为新的leader

【delete.topic.enable】
默认true，允许删除topic


【min.insync.replicas】
acks=-1（一条数据必须写入ISR里所有副本才算成功），你写一条数据只要写入leader就算成功了，不需要等待同步到follower才算写成功。但是此时如果一个follower宕机了，你写一条数据到leader之后，leader也宕机，会导致数据的丢失。

【num.recovery.threads.per.data.dir】
Kafka uses a configurable pool of threads for handling log segments. Currently, this thread pool is used: 
1). When starting normally, to open each partition’s log segments. 
2). When starting after a failure, to check and truncate each partition’s log segments. 
3). When shutting down, to cleanly close log segments. 
**This value is recommended to be increased for installations with data dirs located in RAID array.**
** Note that the number configured is per log directory specified with log.dirs. This means that if num.recovery.threads.per.data.dir is set to 8, and there are 3 paths specified in log.dirs, this is a total of 24 threads**

【auto.create.topics.enable】
The default Kafka configuration specifies that the broker should automatically create a topic under the following circumstances:
• When a producer starts writing messages to the topic
• When a consumer starts reading messages from the topic
• When any client requests metadata for the topic
Set the auto.create.topics.enable configuration to false if you don't want auto-creation

3.2 Topic configuration

The following configuration can be specific to one Topic. So we can have multiple topics with different partition numbers, retention policy, and message path max size, etc..

【num.partitions】
The default number(i.e. default value 1) of log partitions per topic. More partitions allow greater parallelism for consumption, but this will also result in more files across the brokers. Note that the number of partitions for a topic can only be increased, never decreased.

【log.retention.hours】
The minimum age (i.e. default value 168hours/7days) of a log file to be eligible for deletion due to age
Note that retention by time is performed by examining the last modified time (mtime) on each log segment file on disk. Under normal cluster operations, this is the time that the log segment was closed, and represents the timestamp of the last message in the file. However, when using administrative tools to move partitions between brokers, this time is not accurate and will result in excess retention for these partitions.

【log.retention.bytes】
Use the total number of bytes of messages (i.e. default value is 1073741824Byte/1GB) to decide when to delete messages. This number is applied per-partition(not the topic). This means that if you have a topic with 8 partitions, and log.retention.bytes is set to 1 GB, the amount of data retained for the topic will be 8 GB at most.


【log.segment.bytes】
The maximum size (i.e. default is 1073741824Bytes/1GB) of a log segment file. When this size is reached a new log segment will be created. So a partition can have multiple segments to store messages.

【log.retention.check.interval.ms】
The interval(i.e. default value is 300000ms/5minutes) at which log segments are checked to see if they can be deleted according to the retention policies

【message.max.bytes】
The largest record batch size (i.e. default value is 1048588/1MB) allowed by Kafka (after compression if compression is enabled). A producer that tries to send a message larger than this will receive an error back from
the broker, and the message will not be accepted.

There are noticeable performance impacts from increasing the allowable message size. Larger messages will mean that the broker threads that deal with processing network connections and requests will be working longer on each request. Larger messages also increase the size of disk writes, which will impact I/O throughput.

3.2.1 How to choose partition numbers?

There are several factors to consider when choosing the number of partitions:

What is the throughput you expect to achieve for the topic? For example, do you expect to write 100 KB per second or 1 GB per second?

What is the maximum throughput you expect to achieve when consuming from a single partition? You will always have, at most, one consumer reading from a partition, so if you know that your slower consumer writes the data to a database and this database never handles more than 50 MB per second from each thread writing to it, then you know you are limited to 60MB throughput when consuming from a partition.

You can go through the same exercise to estimate the maximum throughput per producer for a single partition, but since producers are typically much faster than consumers, it is usually safe to skip this.

If you are sending messages to partitions based on keys, adding partitions later can be very challenging, so calculate throughput based on your expected future usage, not the current usage.

Consider the number of partitions you will place on each broker and available disk space and network bandwidth per broker.

Avoid overestimating, as each partition uses memory and other resources on

After you have done some estimation on the goal throughput and consumer throughput of the topic, you can divide the goal throughput by the expected consumer throughput and derive the number of partitions. For example, if I want to be able to write and read 1 GB/sec from a topic, and I know each consumer can only process 50 MB/s, then I know I need at least 20 partitions. This way, I can have 20 consumers reading from the topic and achieve 1 GB/sec.

If you don’t have this detailed information, our experience suggests that limiting the size of the partition on the disk to less than 6 GB per day of retention often gives satisfactory results.

3.2.2 Retention policy conflict management

To resolve the retention policy conflict, Kafka uses the first applicable policy. Which means the first applicable retention policy will be used.

For example, if log.retention.hours is set to 24 (1 day) and log.retention.bytes is set to 1 GB, it is possible for messages that are less than 1 day old to get deleted if the total volume of messages over the course of the day is greater than 1 GB. Conversely, if the volume is less than 1 GB, messages can be deleted after 1 day even if the total size of the partition is less than 1 GB.

3.2.3 Coordinations between message.max.bytes and other configurations

The configuration of message.max.bytes must be coordinated with the fetch.message.max.bytes configuration on consumer clients. If this value is smaller than message.max.bytes, then consumers that encounter larger messages will fail to fetch those messages, resulting in a situation where the consumer gets stuck and cannot proceed. The same rule applies to the replica.fetch.max.bytes configuration on the brokers when configured in a cluster.

3.3 Benchmarking your kafka cluster

After your configuration, you may want to test the limit of your cluster. If it does not reach your expectation, you need to tune your configuration again.

Read this https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/KAFKA/Performance+testing#Performancetesting-CommonStats Kafka provides a pair of tools to produce and consume test records to test the throughput of the Kafka cluster.

We need to perform a load test for both, i.e Producer and Consumer, to conclude how many messages a producer can produce and a consumer can consume in a given period of time. The key statistics we are looking for are mentioned below:

Throughput (messages/second) on the size of data

Throughput (messages/second) on the number of messages

Total messages

Total data

Note zk cluster setup can also impact the Kafka performance, in all below test cases, we suppose we have the same zk cluster setup.

3.3.1 Importatn flags

Producer

For running kafka-producer-perf-test.sh, we have the below important flags.

 
 --topic  
 --num-records //total record numbers
 --record-size  //record size in bytes
 --throughput  // The maximum throughput for the test
 --producer-props 
     bootstrap.servers=[serverIP]:9092 
     batch.size=1000 
     acks=1 
     linger.ms=100000 
     buffer.memory=4294967296 
     compression.type=text 
     request.timeout.ms=300000 

Consumer

For running kafka-consumer-perf-test.sh, we have the below important flags.

--topic: The topic to consume from.
--broker-list: The list of brokers which the consumer will connect to (in the form host:port. multiple comma-separated URLs can be provided to allow fail-over) 
--messages: The number of messages to consume.
--threads: Number of processing threads.
--fetch-size: The max message size in bytes which the consumer can consume. 

3.3.2 Test case 1: Single partition, no replication, single producer thread, no compression

# Create a topic with Single partition, no replication, 

bin/kafka-topics.sh --create \
--zookeeper kafka-zk-1:2181,kafka-zk-2:2181,kafka-zk-3:2181 \
--replication-factor 1 \
--partitions 1 \
--topic test1

# run a producer
bin/kafka-producer-perf-test.sh \
--topic test1 \
--num-records 15000000 \
--record-size 100 \
--throughput 15000000 \
--producer-props \
acks=1 \
bootstrap.servers=kf1:9092,kf2:9092,kf3:9092 \
buffer.memory=67108864 \
compression.type=none \
batch.size=8196

# run a consumer
kafka-consumer-perf-test --topic test1 --broker-list kf1:9092,kf2:9092,kf3:9092 --fetch-size 2000 \
--messages 10000000 --threads 2

After running the conumer, it will output the following message.

start.time,end.time,data.consumed.in.MB,MB.sec,data.consumed.in.nMsg,nMsg.sec
2019–03–15 06:53:31,1602019–03–15 06:54:06, 14305.1147,399.9417,10000000,279579.5124

start.time, end.time: shows test start and end time

data.consumed.in.MB: shows the size of all messages consumed

MB.sec: shows how much data transferred in megabytes per second (Throughput on size)

data.consumed.in.nMsg: shows the count of the total messages consumed during this test

nMsg.sec: shows how many messages were consumed in a second (Throughput on the count of messages)

3.3.3 More tests

There can be multiple scenarios and use cases where we can test and take the performance stats for Kafka Producer and Consumer, some of those cases can be :

Change the number of topics

Change the async batch size

Change message size

Change the number of partitions

Change the number of Brokers

Change the number of Producer/Consumer etc

Change the compression Type

Install dokuwiki on Centos7

DokuWiki is a simple to use and highly versatile Open Source wiki software that doesn't require a database. It is loved by users for its clean and readable syntax. The ease of maintenance, backup, and integration makes it an administrator's favorite.

I use it to store all my documentation on all the jobs that I have done.

Official doc: https://www.dokuwiki.org/install:centos

0. Pre-Install

dokuwiki requires only apache web server and php to run. If you want to enable https, you may need to install mod_ssl

# check your centos version
cat /etc/centos-release

# disable your selinux only for httpd, 
semanage permissive -a httpd_t

# add firewall rule
firewall-cmd --zone=public --permanent --add-service=http
firewall-cmd --zone=public --permanent --add-service=https
firewall-cmd --reload


# Install required and useful packages.
sudo yum install -y wget vim bash-completion

# Set up the timezone for Paris.
timedatectl list-timezones
timedatectl set-timezone 'Europe/Paris'

# add repo for installing php 7.1
yum install epel-release
rpm -Uvh https://mirror.webtatic.com/yum/el7/webtatic-release.rpm

# install php 7.1 and required package
yum install -y php71w php71w-cli php71w-fpm php71w-gd php71w-xml php71w-zip

# check php version
php --version
 

1. Install httpd

# Install httpd
yum install httpd mod_ssl

# enable it from boot
systemctl enable httpd

# start the daemon
systemctl start httpd

# check the test page
http://<ip/domainName-of-your-vm>

Add a test.php file under /var/www/html to test your php via apahce

test.php

<?php
phpinfo();
?>

# Restart httpd and check the following url
http://<ip/url-of-your-vm>/test.php

Now everything works, we need to create a virtualhost for dokuwiki. I will give two version One without ssl one with.

doku.conf

<VirtualHost *:80>
   ServerName ec2-52-47-136-8.eu-west-3.compute.amazonaws.com
   ServerAlias 52.47.136.8
   DocumentRoot /var/www/html/dokuwiki
 
  <Directory /var/www/html/dokuwiki>
 Options Indexes FollowSymLinks MultiViews
AllowOverride All
Require  all granted
 </Directory> 
ServerSignature off
ErrorLog /var/log/httpd/error_log
CustomLog /var/log/httpd/access_log combined
 
</VirtualHost>

doku_ssl.conf

<VirtualHost *:80>
    ServerName 104.196.24.4
    ServerAlias wiki.pengfei.org
    Redirect permanent / https://35.243.150.190/
</VirtualHost>
 
If you don't have signed certificate, you need to generate an auto-signed certificate
<code>
# generate private key and certificate
openssl req -x509 -nodes -days 965 -newkey rsa:2048 -keyout wiki.pengfei.org.key -out wiki.pengfei.org.crt
 
# copy them to the standard place
cp wiki.pengfei.org.key /etc/pki/tls/private/.
cp wiki.pengfei.org.crt /etc/pki/tls/certs/.
</code>
 
<VirtualHost *:443>
   ServerName 104.196.24.4
   ServerAlias wiki.pengfei.org
   DocumentRoot /var/www/html/dokuwiki
 
  <Directory /var/www/html/dokuwiki>
 Options Indexes FollowSymLinks MultiViews
AllowOverride All
Require  all granted
 </Directory> 
ServerSignature off
ErrorLog /var/log/httpd/error_log
CustomLog /var/log/httpd/access_log combined
 
 
    SSLEngine       on
    SSLProtocol all -SSLv2
    SSLCipherSuite ALL:!ADH:!EXPORT:!SSLv2:RC4+RSA:+HIGH:+MEDIUM
 
    SSLCertificateFile      /etc/pki/tls/certs/wiki.pengfei.org.crt
    SSLCertificateKeyFile   /etc/pki/tls/private/wiki.pengfei.org.key
    SSLCertificateChainFile /etc/pki/tls/certs/wiki.pengfei.org.crt
 
</VirtualHost>

2. Download or use existing dokuwiki files

Get the dokuwiki source, unzip it and put it /var/www/html

# change owner to apache
chown -R apache:root /var/www/html/dokuwiki

#If you download it as new dokuwiki, you will need to visit http://<ip/url-of-your-vm>/install.php first.

In this page, you will need to set up the root user login and pwd, and give a name to your dokuwiki website.

3. Update your dokuwiki

1. Replace the data directory in the new release by the old data directory which has all your work 2. Replace the conf directory in the new release by the old conf directory which has all your configuration

4. Install plugin

4.1 Export to pdf plugin

I used DW2pdf plugin. Login to dokuwiki as admin, then go to admin dashboard→plugin manager→ search dw2pdf.

This plugin requires a php dependencies mbstring

yum install php71w-mbstring
systemctl restart httpd

common problems

Can't open file due to permission.

1. Check the /var/www/html/dokuwiki owner and acl 2. disable selinux

Install mysql on centos7

There is a page with all intallation guide of installing mysql on all linux

https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/linux-installation.html

Get the rpm source repo

You can find all the available rpm in here, https://dev.mysql.com/downloads/repo/yum/

download and install it.

yum localinstall mysql57-community-release-el7-11.noarch.rpm 

The installation command adds the MySQL Yum repository to your system's repository list and downloads the GnuPG key to check the integrity of the software packages. See Section 2.1.3.2, “Signature Checking Using GnuPG” for details on GnuPG key checking.

You can check that the MySQL Yum repository has been successfully added by the following command (for Fedora, replace yum in the command with dnf):

yum repolist enabled | grep "mysql.*-community.*"

Select your mysql version

To install the latest release from the latest GA series, no configuration is needed. To install the latest release from a specific series other than the latest GA series, disable the subrepository for the latest GA series and enable the subrepository for the specific series before running the installation command. If your platform supports yum-config-manager, you can do that by issuing these commands, which disable the subrepository for the 5.7 series and enable the one for the 5.6 series:

shell> sudo yum-config-manager --disable mysql57-community
shell> sudo yum-config-manager --enable mysql56-community

Besides using yum-config-manager or the dnf config-manager command, you can also select a release series by editing manually the /etc/yum.repos.d/mysql-community.repo file. This is a typical entry for a release series' subrepository in the file:

[mysql57-community]
name=MySQL 5.7 Community Server
baseurl=http://repo.mysql.com/yum/mysql-5.7-community/el/6/$basearch/
enabled=1
gpgcheck=1
gpgkey=file:///etc/pki/rpm-gpg/RPM-GPG-KEY-mysql

Find the entry for the subrepository you want to configure, and edit the enabled option. Specify enabled=0 to disable a subrepository, or enabled=1 to enable a subrepository. For example, to install MySQL 5.6, make sure you have enabled=0 for the above subrepository entry for MySQL 5.7, and have enabled=1 for the entry for the 5.6 series:

# Enable to use MySQL 5.6
[mysql56-community]
name=MySQL 5.6 Community Server
baseurl=http://repo.mysql.com/yum/mysql-5.6-community/el/6/$basearch/
enabled=1
gpgcheck=1
gpgkey=file:///etc/pki/rpm-gpg/RPM-GPG-KEY-mysql

You should only enable subrepository for one release series at any time. When subrepositories for more than one release series are enabled, the latest series will be used by Yum.

Verify that the correct subrepositories have been enabled and disabled by running the following command and checking its output (for Fedora, replace yum in the command with dnf):

shell> yum repolist enabled | grep mysql

Install the mysql server

shell> sudo yum install mysql-community-server

Start the server daemon

shell> sudo service mysqld start
Starting mysqld:[ OK ]

shell> sudo service mysqld status
mysqld (pid 3066) is running.

At the initial start up of the server, the following happens, given that the data directory of the server is empty:

The server is initialized.

SSL certificate and key files are generated in the data directory.

The validate_password plugin is installed and enabled.

A superuser account 'root'@'localhost is created. A password for the superuser is set and stored in the error log file. To reveal it, use the following command:

shell> sudo grep 'temporary password' /var/log/mysqld.log

Change the root password as soon as possible by logging in with the generated, temporary password and set a custom password for the superuser account:

shell> mysql -uroot -p
mysql> ALTER USER 'root'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'MyNewPass4!';

Install mysql server on mode offline

In most cases, you need to install the mysql-community-server, mysql-community-client, mysql-community-libs, mysql-community-common, and mysql-community-libs-compat packages to get a functional, standard MySQL installation. To perform such a standard, basic installation, go to the folder that contains all those packages.

You can download all these packages from here https://dev.mysql.com/downloads/mysql/

-rw-r--r--   1 pliu bioaster  24M Nov 14 10:52 mysql-community-client-5.7.20-1.el7.x86_64.rpm
-rw-r--r--   1 pliu bioaster 272K Nov 14 10:52 mysql-community-common-5.7.20-1.el7.x86_64.rpm
-rw-r--r--   1 pliu bioaster 2.2M Nov 14 10:52 mysql-community-libs-5.7.20-1.el7.x86_64.rpm
-rw-r--r--   1 pliu bioaster 2.1M Nov 14 10:52 mysql-community-libs-compat-5.7.20-1.el7.x86_64.rpm
-rw-r--r--   1 pliu bioaster 164M Nov 14 10:52 mysql-community-server-5.7.20-1.el7.x86_64.rpm

sudo yum install mysql-community-{server,client,common,libs}-*

It does not work, it requires some other dependencies.

Install mariadb on centos 7

MariaDB is a drop-in replacement for MySQL. It is easy to install, offers many speed and performance improvements, and is easy to integrate into most MySQL deployments. Answers for compatibility questions can be found at: MariaDB versus MySQL Compatibility. MariaDB offers more storage engines than MySQL, including Cassandra (NoSQL, in MariaDB Version 10), XtraDB (drop-in replacement for InnoDB), and OQGRAPH (in MariaDB Version 10).

Pre-Flight Check These instructions are intended for installing MariaDB on a single CentOS 7 node. I’ll be working from a Liquid Web Self Managed CentOS 7 server, and I’ll be logged in as root.

sudo yum install mariadb-server
sudo systemctl start mariadb
# Be sure that MySQL/MariaDB starts at boot:
sudo systemctl enable mariadb

systemctl status mariadb
# during the mysql secure installation, you will set the password for root 
mysql_secure_installation

Connect to mysql server

mysql -u root -p

Create database and user

# create database
create database retail_db;

# create user with localhost access, to give remote access, you need to change localhost to a ip or url.
CREATE USER 'newuser'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'password';
create user 'retail_dba'@'localhost' identified by 'retail_dba_pwd';

# drop user
DROP USER ‘username’@‘localhost’;

# grant access 
# the first * is the database name, the second * is the table name
GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON * . * TO 'newuser'@'localhost';
# 
grant all privileges on retail_db. * to 'retail_dba'@'localhost';

# create user to access database
GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON *.* TO 'username'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'password';
grant all privileges on retail_db to 'retail_dba'@'localhost' identified by 'retail_dba_pwd';

# active permission changes
FLUSH PRIVILEGES;

Exporting the Database

The mysqldump console utility is used to export databases to SQL text files, making it relatively easy to transfer and move around. You will need the database name itself as well as the username and password to an account with privileges allowing at least full read only access to the database.

Export your database using the following command structure:

mysqldump -u username -p database_name > data-dump.sql

username is the username you can log in to the database with database_name is the name of the database that will be exported data-dump.sql is the file in the current directory that the output will be saved to The command will produce no visual output, but you can inspect the contents of filename.sql to check if it's a legitimate SQL dump file by running the following command:

head -n 5 data-dump.sql

Import .sql file to database

mysql -u retail_dba -p retail_db < /tmp/retail_db.sql 

Grant remote access to mysql/mariadb server

0. Configure your firewall to allow access of port 3306

# In centos7, we use firewalld. So the command is

firewall-cmd --permanent --add-port=3306/tcp

firewall-cmd --reload

1. find the default config file

# The config file location depends on your linux distribution
/etc/my.cnf                              (*nix/BSD)
$MYSQL_HOME/my.cnf                       (*nix/BSD) *Most Notably /etc/mysql/my.cnf
SYSCONFDIR/my.cnf                        (*nix/BSD)

# In centos7, it located at /etc/my.cnf
> vim /etc/my.cnf

# locate the [mysqld] section, if you see the following line
    # skip-networking refuse all remote access
    skip-networking
    ...
    # only accept the ip address in the conf
    bind-address = <some ip-address>
    ... 
    
# remove or comment these two lines. Your mysql server is ready to accept any remote connection.    

To make this take effet, you need to restart the server

systemctl restart mariadb

2. Grant privileges to user and table

# The first * in *.* is the name of the database, the second is the name of the table
# 'root' is the user name
# The % in '192.168.100.%' is the wildcard, so all ip looks like 192.168.100.* is acceptable
# The  IDENTIFIED BY 'pwd' can be omitted, if omitted, you don't need to enter password to connect
# WITH GRANT OPTION is optional which means you give user the right to grant access to the database  

GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON *.* TO 'root'@'192.168.100.%' IDENTIFIED BY 'pwd' WITH GRANT OPTION;

# The above command gives user root connected from 192.168.100.* with password 'pwd' all access on all tables with grant option. 

# Suppose we have a database named retail_db, and you want give user retail_dba access on all tables in the db, you can use the following command

GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON retail_db.* TO 'retail_dba'@'192.168.100.%' IDENTIFIED BY 'pwd'

# If you want retail_dba connected from 172.17.*.* does not require password, you can use the following command

GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON retail_db.* TO 'retail_dba'@'172.17.%.%'

# Unlike, postgresql, a user can have a distinct password for each remote host.

# After you add all the privileges, you can check all user with remote access privileges with the below command.

SELECT User, Host FROM mysql.user WHERE Host <> 'localhost';

Remove priviliges

# 1. You need to remove the privileges on the database
REVOKE ALL PRIVILEGES ON retail_db.* FROM 'retail_dba'@'172.17.%.%';

# 2. Then remove the user
drop user 'retail_dba'@'172.17.%.%'

JDBC driver

https://mariadb.com/kb/en/library/about-mariadb-connector-j/

Use redis for file blocking

Additional notes for Redis vs. APCu on Memory Caching

APCu is faster at local caching than Redis. If you have enough memory, use APCu for memory caching and Redis for file locking. If you are low on memory, use Redis for both.

yum install epel-release
yum update
# install redis server
yum install redis
# install php71 redis driver
php71w-pecl-redis

#start redis
systemctl start/stop/status/restart redis

#run redis at bootup
systemctl enable redis

#verify redis, it should answer PONG
redis-cli ping

Persistence Options

Redis provides two options for disk persistence:

Point-in-time snapshots of the dataset, made at specified intervals (RDB).

Append-only logs of all the write operations performed by the server (AOF).

Each option has its own pros and cons which are detailed in the Redis documentation. For the greatest level of data safety, consider running both persistence methods.

Because the Point-in-time snapshot persistence is enabled by default, you only need to set up AOF persistence:

#Edit /etc/redis.conf, change the following lines
appendonly yes
appendfsync everysec

Restart redis to make it effective

Basic System Tuning

To improve Redis performance, set the Linux kernel overcommit memory setting to 1:

sudo sysctl vm.overcommit_memory=1

This immediately changes the overcommit memory setting, but the change will not persist across reboots. To make it permanent, add vm.overcommit_memory = 1 to /etc/sysctl.conf:

sudo vim /etc/sysctl.conf

vm.overcommit_memory = 1

Edit config.php for owncloud to use redis

'memcache.locking' => '\\OC\\Memcache\\Redis',
  'redis' => 
  array (
    'host' => 'localhost',
    'port' => 6379,
  ),

Date : 31/03/2015

Participants : JG, TLC, AC, PV, NS, AT

Précédente réunion le 20/03/2015

Ordre du jour

Les sujets barrés sont en attente.
Les sujets surlignés en gris sont traités s'il y a assez de temps
Les sujets surlignés en rouge sont prioritaires.

Attention : eclipse solaire à 10h30

Question | Quoi? | Qui? | Avancement
1 | Suivie des tickets | NS | RAS
2 | REALISM | NS | Constitution d'un lot de données test et développement du parser de curation
3 | eSamples/développement | AC+TLC | Priorité sur le passage à Symfony et l'authentification
3 | eSamples/recueil des besoins | AC+TLC | A priori, toutes les UTECs sont pour passer au code barre + douchette/lecteur de plaque. Bilan à faire sur les info présentes dans les fichiers Excel (sont-elles toutes associées à 1 projet), a priori pas de double enregistrement
3 | eSamples/suivi | AC+TLC | publication des avancées à BIOASTER en LabMeeting
4 | Workflow management et plateforme bio-info | PV | Rédaction du plan projet en cours. SysFera OK pour une prestation HTcondor
5 | OpenStack et accounting | NS+PV+JG | En stand by
6 | Hébergement au CCIN2P3 et convention | JG+PV | Suivi du backup sur GPFS. Organisation de points mensuels avec Ghita. JG doit relancer Loïc et Rémi sur GPFS/NFSv4 et TSM
7 | <Déploiement de Galaxy, SequenceServer, de ViroBlast, de SecureBlast ou de Gene Pattern | TLC | Go pour Galaxy
8 | OBJECTIFS UTEC6 | NS | Finalisation
9 | Data management | JG | L'UTEC3 discute avec l'AQ pour définir une arborescence des données. AC va faire du support actifs avec l'UTEC2. REALISM, droits de lecture/écriture à vérifier. JG doit former AC et TLC à l'administration d'OwnCloud. La partie administration système serait reprise par le nouveau sysadmin
10 | Tarification UTEC6 | NS | Travail en cours avec Tatiana
11 | Saisie des temps | NS | Cf. ci-dessous

Saisie des temps

Ligne UTEC6 : à ne pas utiliser par les membres de l'UTEC6! Ligne uniquement pour les membres des autres UTEC

Ligne setup PT6/WP0 : montage des projets internes, rédaction de PQP, tarification UTEC6

Ligne setup PT6/WP99 : réunion bio-info, réunion d'équipe, test de développement, veille technologique et scientifique

Ligne setup UTECx/WP99 : support aux UTECx (ex. troubleshooting Miseq)

Ligne préprojet : projets collaboratifs (ex. projets européens), prospection

Ligne autres : labmeeting, congrès (or prospection), formation (hors projet)

Ligne DAFSI : réunion comité de développement SI, socle informatique, etc.